<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The advantages of the present settlement, and the great danger of a relapse</title>
            <author>Defoe, Daniel, 1661?-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D827B</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12729928</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12729928</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199297</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 359:3e)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The advantages of the present settlement, and the great danger of a relapse</title>
                  <author>Defoe, Daniel, 1661?-1731.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Authorship uncertain; possibly written by Defoe. Cf. Moore, J.R. Checklist of the writings of Daniel Defoe, 1971; BM.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed, July 4, 1689. J. Fraser"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Michigan Libraries.</note>
                  <note>Reel guide for Wing Unit 10 incorrectly places item at 339:24.</note>
                  <note>Entry for A601 cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Bound with C1a, J1264, K577, J1200A, and V535.</note>
                  <note>"Books lately printed for Richard Chiswell": p. [1]-[2].</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199297:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ADVANTAGES OF THE PRESENT SETTLEMENT, AND THE GREAT DANGER OF A RELAPSE.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>LICENSED, <hi>July</hi> 4. 1689.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. Fraſer.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi rend="blackletterType">Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:199297:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199297:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE ADVANTAGES OF THE Preſent SETTLEMENT, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE wonderful Revolution that hath fallen out in the Iſland of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ſince <hi>September</hi> laſt, 1688. is juſtly at preſent the diſcourſe and amazement of all <hi>Europe;</hi> but chiefly in the three Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland, England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> whoſe Inhabitants are the Parties moſt concerned in it; and no wonder, ſince a greater Deliverance, more unexpected, and that hath plainer Characters of a Divine Contrivance and Conduct, hath neither been heard of, nor ſeen, in any place of the World, in any of the former Ages of it. But there is a greater Wonder now to be obſerved amongſt us than the Deliverance we have received (if any thing can be greater) <hi>viz.</hi> That there are many of us who ſeem to be much diſcontented with it, and expreſs themſelves in ſuch a manner, as if they were offended with Heaven it ſelf, for being ſo propitious to us; and ſeem ungratefully to envy his Honour, whom God made the great Inſtrument of our Deliverance. Strange! that another Change ſhould come under the deſires of reaſonable men, which muſt of abſolute neceſſity occaſion a fatal Relapſe into the ſame Miſeries we were ſo deeply plunged, and likewiſe occaſion the inevitable and laſting ruine, not only of our potent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer, but alſo of all thoſe Royal Branches of the Royal Family, in whoſe proſperity all the hopes of <hi>England</hi>'s Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs are certainly repoſed.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199297:3"/>
            <p>While I frequently hear ſuch Murmurings and Whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perings as tend to ſuch a fatal End, I cannot but be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, both with aſtoniſhment and grief: aſtoniſhment, it being wonderful men ſhould be diſpleaſed with their own Safety and Happineſs: and grief, it being eaſie to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend thoſe ill Conſequences to the Publick, that uſually attend ſuch Diſcontents and undutiful Murmurings, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly and induſtriouſly promoted.</p>
            <p>And though I am very ſenſible of my own utter unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for ſo great an undertaking, as the allaying of thoſe Heats and Animoſities that ſo much diſturb the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs and peace we have in our hands, if we would but embrace it, and be contented to enjoy it: yet I hope I ſhall be forgiven of all, even of thoſe who perhaps may have an averſion to this Diſcourſe, for the very ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my Intention; for the Author aſſures his Reader, that his Condition is ſo obſcure, his Acquaintance in the World ſo narrow, and (as you will eaſily perceive by this Pamphlet, both as to the matter and ſtyle of it, which falls ſo much below the dignity of the Subject, and is ſo rude and unpoliſht) his Habitation is ſomewhat ſolitary, and in a manner rural; and thereforefore it cannot be imagined that Self-intereſt ſhould ſhare in his Deſign: no, ſuffer him only quietly to put in his poor mite into the Treaſury, and if he in any meaſure contribute to the Publick Peace and Happineſs of that Church of which he glories to be a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, even that of <hi>England,</hi> as it is now by Law eſtabliſhed; and of that Kingdom, which he accounts it the greateſt part of his civil happineſs to be a Subject in, he is ſufficiently ſatisfied; which deſign he is ſure no man can poſſibly blame.</p>
            <p>I would therefore, as an Introduction to what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, ask but this queſtion of thoſe Perſons that ſeem ſo diſcontented with our preſent Tranquility. Gentlemen, what is it you would be at? what do you deſire? If they ſpeak plainly, and give a round anſwer to this queſtion, it muſt be this; We would have King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY</hi> dethroned again, and have them either voluntarily to return back from whence they came, or elſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199297:3"/> to be ſent back again by force; we would have King <hi>JAMES</hi> the Second reſtored to his Crown and Dignity, and reinſtated in his Throne and Government. This muſt be the Anſwer, or elſe I cannot imagine what ſome men keep ſuch a noiſe for. Fair and ſoft, Sirs! This is a demand of the greateſt conſequence and importance that ever <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> heard; I aſſure you it's not likely to be yielded to without very mature and ſerious deliberation; and I am very confident, would men ſuffer their Reaſon to act free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without the ſtrong Biaſs of Intereſt or Paſſion, they would ſee it as unfit to be asked, as they certainly muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of having it granted. For, upon the whole, the yielding to the Propoſal, would be a fatal Relapſe into all thoſe Miſeries, under which we ſo lately groaned; and as it is in the caſe of a Relapſe into the ſame Diſtempers from which Patients ſeemed almoſt to be freed, their laſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is much more dangerous than their firſt; ſo undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly it would be with us. And this will the more clearly appear, upon a ſerious conſideration of theſe three things.
<list>
                  <item>1. What condition we were in before the happy arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of their preſent Majeſties.</item>
                  <item>2. What condition we are now in by this happy Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</item>
                  <item>3. What a miſerable condition we muſt of neceſſity fall into upon ſuch a ſecond Revolution as would ſatisfy ſome mens deſires.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe, it's to be hoped that you will not take it ill, if upon your propoſal, we make a review of that ſtate you would reduce us to. I aſſure you, we are as ſorry, even for King <hi>JAMES</hi>'s ſake, that the reflection is ſo unpleaſant, as poſſibly you can be; yet if we find it to be a miſerable Condition, you will, I hope, excuſe us, if we be not willing deſperately to ruſh our ſelves into it again.</p>
            <p>Now I know not what in all the World is dear to a reaſonable Creature, that was not (as our Circumſtances were) in the greateſt hazard of being utterly loſt. For what is it that is moſt dear to us as Chriſtians? Religion.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199297:4"/> What is moſt dear to us as <hi>Engliſh</hi> men? The enjoyment of our Liberties and Properties, ſecured to us by the Laws of the Land. What is moſt dear to us as individual ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? The ſafety and protection of our Lives, Perſons and Families. Now I dare appeal to all unprejudiced men, whether in any Nation under Heaven, that was ſo firmly in the poſſeſſion of all theſe as we were a few years ago, they were ever in greater danger of being utterly loſt, than they were here in <hi>England;</hi> ſo that the preſervation of them is next to a Miracle.</p>
            <p>That there was a Deſign to ſubvert the eſtabliſhed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of this Church and Kingdom, I hope no man will ſo much as queſtion. King <hi>JAMES</hi> did quickly let us ſee what was ſo much feared by many before he came to the Crown, That it was great folly to imagine that a Prince ſo great a Zealot for his own Perſuaſion, would not think it his Duty to uſe that Power God had given him, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of that Religion he was ſo Zealous for; which could never be without the Extirpation of the Eſtabliſhed Religion, accounted by him a Peſtilent Hereſie. To this end tended the Erecting of Chappels for Popiſh Devotion, and Publick Schools for Popiſh Education. Was it for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that an Ambaſſador was reſident at <hi>Rome?</hi> And a <hi>Nuncio</hi> publickly entertained here, for a conſtant Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Rome?</hi> Why were all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Nobility and Gentry turned out of all places either of Honour, Profit, or Truſt; and Papiſts put in their Rooms? What could be the deſign of that ducoy of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> at a time, when ſince the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of thoſe unhappy diviſions of Proteſtants here at home, there was never leſs need of it? When not any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Party amongſt us, did ſo much as Petition for it; when the Generality of Diſſenters were ſo well ſatisfied with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that there were never fairer hopes of perfect Unity amongſt us. But this was the matter; the diviſion of Proteſtants amongſt themſelves would weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the whole Body of them, and render them the more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of an eaſie overthrow; a deſign, which the wiſer
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199297:4"/> ſort of Diſſenters quickly ſaw, and even the generality of them in a ſhort time were ſatisfied in. For ſince it's as eaſie for the <hi>Arctick</hi> and <hi>Antarctick</hi> Poles to meet together; or for the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> to be in Conjunction, as to reconcile Infallibility of one Religion, with a Toleration of all; the neceſſity of Extirpating all Hereticks, with a Connivance at all Hereſies; all were eaſily convinced what ſuch a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration tended to, and none were entrapped in the Snare, or trepanned with the Cheat, but a few hot-headed Zealots, ready to Sacrifice all to Ambition and Revenge. What could be the deſign of putting Papiſts in for Heads of Houſes, Maſters and Fellows of Colleges, in our famous Univerſities? What could be the deſign of Erecting a High Commiſſion Court for Ecclefiaſtical Cauſes, for the ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and depriving of Biſhops and Clergy; which was juſtly termed the New Inquiſition of <hi>England?</hi> Why was that enſnaring Declaration ſo violently, and yet ſo unneceſſarily preſt upon the Clergy, to be read in Churches; and Seven Biſhops impriſoned, and the whole Clergy of the Kingdom threatned with Deprivation for Non-Compliance? If theſe things, and a great many more, will not ſatisfie men, That there was a real Deſign of ſubverting our Religion, I know not what will.</p>
            <p>Yet to demonſtrate this matter to the full, conſider only the mighty endeavours that were uſed to abrogate the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws and Teſt; in which the King uſed ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, that he truly took methods too much below Royal Dignity to effect it. What a mean office for a King to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an earneſt Sollicitor of his Subjects, to that which they could not in Conſcience nor Honour yield to; and then a diſobliger of all his Kingdom, for removing them from all places, upon ſo neceſſary a refuſal! The deſign muſt be mighty great, when Arts both ſo mean and ſo harſh, were uſed to accompliſh it. But this was it; The Papiſts had then ſtood upon even ground with all other Subjects; and the great advantage of Authority on their ſide, would quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have raiſed their Ground above us; the doors of both Houſes of Parliament had been ſet wide open to them,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199297:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> whence the Houſe of Peers might quickly have been filled with new Creations, and the Houſe of Commons as quickly made Popiſh by Force or Fraud in Elections, Corporations being framed and regulated agreeable to the deſign; and what could be then expected, but a ſudden Eſtabliſhment of Popery? The whole Nation did ſee this Project ſo clearly, that the greateſt part of the Diſſenters were ſo ſenſible of the miſchief, that though they had ſmarted ſomewhat hardly under the Laſh of the Penal Laws but a little while before, yet they would rather ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Continuance of them, than run the hazard of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ining the ſubſtance and being of the Proteſtant Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; nor could all the virulent Pamphlets thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to exaſperate them, by a Tragical Commemoration of their former Suffering by the Penal Laws, ever perſwade them ſo far out of their Senſes, as not to be fully aſſured, that the Little Finger of the Popiſh Inquiſition would be heavier upon them, than the Loins of all the Penal Laws made ſince the Reformation againſt them. And indeed to the Fidelity of that Party at that Critical time, are we to aſcribe a great ſhare of the diſappointment the Popiſh Party met with, being much chafed, that the Grand Cheat of the Toleration had no better ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>And as all theſe plain matters of fact, are more than ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to convince us of the Miſchievous Deſign of ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Eſtabliſhed Religion in theſe Kingdoms; ſo are they a plain and evident proof, that there was certainly a Private League between the Late King <hi>James</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King for bringing this to paſs, tho there were nothing elſe to evince is. For it could never be hoped that the Popiſh Party here in <hi>England</hi> could do it, their Strength and Intereſt were not ſufficient to accompliſh ſuch a Deſign. There was a fine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my indeed, but moſt of them Proteſtants, who would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be commanded by Popiſh Officers, to ruine their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for men muſt certainly fight very faintly, when the edge of their Swords is turned againſt themſelves, and their ſucceſs is certain deſolation to their Country. From whence one of theſe two things muſt follow; either that King <hi>James</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199297:5"/> had no Reſolution to change the Religion of this Nation, the contrary of which appears by what hath been ſaid; and beſides, to ſay ſo, is to put the greateſt affront and diſhonour upon the Late King that can be, and calls his Wiſdom and Diſcretion highly in queſtion, in the conduct of his Affairs; that he ſhould do all theſe mean, harſh, and ſuſpitious things before alledged, for no other end, but to bring an obloquy upon himſelf, to render his Government uneaſie, fearful, and ſuſpected, and to diſoblige all the three Kingdoms. But if it cannot be admitted, that a perſon of any common ſeuſe or reaſon, ſhould be guilty of ſo much Indiſcretion, that might in the end prove ſo fatal to himſelf, then we muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that ſome Foreign Power was certainly to be made uſe of; ſince no reaſonable man propoſeth to himſelf any end, but withall he propoſeth means proportionate to that end, in order to the acquiring of it: and now we would fain learn, what other Force can ſo much as come under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of being made uſe of, but the <hi>French?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now that which makes this Deſign abundantly the more inexcuſable in it ſelf, and the more inſupportable to us, is this; That this Church, and the Religion profeſſed in it, run ſuch a great hazard from a Prince, from whom the Members of that Church, and Profeſſors of that Religion, had all the reaſon in the world to expect much kinder uſage. For I am ſure never any Prince could be more highly obliged by Subjects, than King <hi>James</hi> was by the Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> both before, and after he was King. Not to run ſo far back as the unhappy Wars in his Father's time of ever Bleſſed and Glorious Memory, when the Church of <hi>England</hi> was ruined, and a great many of the Members of it, of all degrees and conditions, expoſed to the greateſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, for their firm adherence to the Intereſt of the Crown. Nor yet to ſpeak of his Late Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's happy Reſtauration; it's enough only to reflect upon our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful behaviour to King <hi>James</hi> himſelf, both when Duke, and King. Who were the great oppoſers of the Bill of Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in Parliament, both in the Houſe of Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and out of Parliament all the Kingdom over; and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199297:6"/> preferred their ſtanding faſt to the Duke's Intereſt at that time, to all their own Intereſt in the World: What Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, Diſgraces, Inſolencies, nay Threats were caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and uſed towards us, we very well remember. Was there ever any King received by his People, or proclaimed in all Places, with greater Satisfaction, Joy and Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than he was? For who then doubted of the Sincerity of King <hi>James</hi> the Juſt? Who were they that ſo readily ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Revenue of the Crown, and gave larger ſupplies than the neceſſity of Affairs required? Who were they that ſtood the Shock, and ventured their Lives in ſuppreſſing of that dangerous Rebellion of <hi>Monmouth?</hi> Were they not all Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who preſerved the Crown for King <hi>James</hi> before he came to the poſſeſſion of it, by oppoſing the Bill of Excluſion; and kept it upon his Head when he was poſſeſſed of it, by ſuppreſſing <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Rebellion? And this brings to my mind an Expreſſion, in the <hi>Oxford</hi> Reaſons, againſt ſigning the Addreſs of their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Dr. <hi>Parker;</hi> for being told that their refuſal of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs would exaſperate the King, and move him to take rougher Methods againſt the Church; their Anſwer was, That if the remembrance of the Services of the Church to the Crown in thoſe two Affairs, of the Bill of Excluſion, and <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Rebellion, were not ſufficient to ſecure the King's kindneſs to, and protection of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and its Members, the ſigning of ſuch inſignificant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes would never do it; and truly I cannot tell what elſe could do it.</p>
            <p>But the truth of it is, the Papiſts have all along, upon all occaſions ſo ill requited the Fidelity of the Proteſtants to their Popiſh Princes, as if they had a mind never more to be obliged in that nature. I need not ſpeak of the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations put upon Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and the barbarous uſage ſhewed them in a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while after; nor of former dealings of that kind in <hi>France:</hi> the preſent King of <hi>France</hi> hath demonſtrated this to the full; he ows his poſſeſſion of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and conſequently all his Glory he ſo proudly boaſts of, to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199297:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> the firm adherence of his Proteſtant Subjects to his Intereſt. He hath ſeveral times publickly owned this, and yet his Cruelty to them hath far ſurpaſſed all Heathen Barbarity. And now I am very ſorry that ſuch a hearty Endeavour to ſubvert the Religion eſtabliſhed in this Church, which could not be, without the ruine of thoſe, to whom the late King <hi>JAMES</hi> was ſo highly obliged, hath given ſuch another freſh Inſtance, that Popery will not ſuffer Kings ſo much as to be grateful to their Subjects; for by this means they have more than ſatisfied the World, that it's utterly unſafe for a Proteſtant Kingdom to be under the Government of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prince.</p>
            <p>But ſince all men have neither that knowledge of, nor that zeal for their Religion, that it were heartily to be wiſhed they had, yet every man is very ſenſible, when their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Properties, and the Laws by which they are ſecured, are invaded: and leſt the Endeavours to ſubvert Religion, ſhould not have been ſufficient to have provoked the Nation, there was added to this a plain Invaſion of the Rights of the Subject, and of the Laws upon which they are grounded; to let the World know, that there was no miſtake in thoſe men, who affirmed, that Popery could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be introduced into this Kingdom, unleſs Slavery uſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in. It were endleſs to make inſtances of this; the Maſter and Fellows of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Colledge are a ſufficient proof of this, who were deprived of their Freeholds, by a moſt arbitrary Sentence of a Court, that in the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of it, was utterly illegal; and in an Affair of this nature, a Judge altogether incompetent; where the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concerned were admitted to no legal Tryal, before the competent Judges, by a Jury of the Vicinage, as in thoſe Caſes is the Law of the Nation; but were removed by Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who had no more right to diſpoſeſs them of their Freeholds, than the Perſons, receiving ſuch an injurious Sentence, had to diſpoſſeſs their very Judges of theirs. And it was no wonder that the general Cry of the Nation, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that unjuſt and Arbitrary Sentence, was, All our Freeholds and Eſtates ſhake by this Sentence.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:199297:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Another proof of this Invaſion of our Rights and Eſtates was, the moſt exorbitant and extravagant Fines, put upon perſons by the plain Arbitrary Will of the Judges, as if they would declare to the World, their deſign was rather to ruine the Delinquent, than puniſh the Delinquency. This was ſo frequent, that every Term ſhewed how eaſily, for very ſmall faults, men might be ruined in their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes in a trice.</p>
            <p>The invading the Rights of Corporations, was more than ſufficient proof, that our Liberties, Eſtates and Laws were in the greateſt hazard. The deſpoiling them of all their Ancient Privileges, ſtruck at the very Foundation of the Government it ſelf; the altering all the Ancient Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions in chooſing of perſons for Repreſentatives in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſtruck at the very Fountain of our Laws, both in being, and to be made.</p>
            <p>But above all things tending to the ruine of all our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity in our Laws, Liberties and Properties, none is more worthy of our ſerious conſideration, than that <hi>Hellow</hi> of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing Power, that would have devoured all at a morſel, and ſwallowed all at one draught, if need had been; there was no Law, no Privilege able to ſtand in the way of this <hi>Leviathan.</hi> This was ſuch a Power, that once being yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, in the full latitude it was claimed, would have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered all Laws in <hi>England</hi> not only uncertain and inſecure, but utterly needleſs; nay, altogether ridiculous. For to what purpoſe ſhould the Nation be put to ſo much trouble and charge, to elect Repreſentatives for the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; or why ſhould Perſons, who have either a natural Right, as Noblemen, or a deputed Right, as Commoners, go from all parts of the Kingdom, to enact Laws for the good and profit of the Realm, if the Sovereign Power can diſpenſe with them, whenever their backs are turned? To what purpoſe is all this waſt? Or why ſhould the Nation be fooled with Laws, which when made, promiſe us the greateſt ſecurity, in all things that are moſt valuable; when in the mean time, at the mere will of the Prince in diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with theſe, all our Security is turned into Deſpair; and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199297:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> all our Expectations, grounded on thoſe Laws, wholly fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and quite blown up?</p>
            <p>The Impriſonment of the Seven Biſhops, who all deſerve to have Statues erected to their Memories, for ſo couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſtemming that Tide of Oppreſſion, that was like to have ſunk us into the deepeſt miſeries both in our Religious and Civil Rights: This Impriſonment, I ſay, tho it was diſmal and gloomy, yet bleſſed be God, their Tryal that followed upon it, occaſioned the abſolute baffling of that Diſpenſing Power, by thoſe learned and ſtout Gentlemen, their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, who dared at ſuch a time, to vindicate our Laws from ſo much Violence, and our Liberties from ſuch Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>But then if we add to all this, That we were not ſo much as ſafe in our Perſons and Families, our Condition will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the more deplorable. How many were there, who abandoned their Native Country, upon the apprehenſion of thoſe Dangers that Innocency it ſelf was not able to ſecure them from? Was not the Lord <hi>De La Mere</hi> expoſed to the greateſt danger by a falſe Accuſation, and preſſed earneſtly to acknowledg a Capital Crime, of which in the end he was found innocent? Was not the now Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> forced to fly for his Life, and could hardly obtain the liberty of breathing in a Foreign Air, or the benefit of the Protection of Foreign States and Princes; excepted in all Acts of Grace as the greateſt Criminal? And yet upon the ſtricteſt enquiry into the reaſon, why Royal Power was ſo armed againſt this Perſon, it will be hard to find any other, than this, that he was the Author of the <hi>Hiſtory of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation;</hi> which will be a ſufficient Monument for that Great Man when he is dead, and for his undaunted Courage and Zeal for, and great Abilities and Induſtry in defending a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion his then Majeſty had ſo great an averſion to. Add to this, the cruel Corporal Puniſhments, inflicted upon ſeveral Perſons both in City and Country. In fine, The unſpeakable Oppreſſion of the Souldiery, by vertue of whoſe quartering at pleaſure, neither men's Families or Perſons were ſecure from the greateſt violence; moſt of the Corporations of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are too too able to give a ſad and deplorable account of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199297:8"/> this, who felt the Inſolencies of Mercenary men, permitted in all their Extravagant Miſchiefs, to inure the Nation by degrees to Slavery and Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>I know that many will not be pleaſed with ſuch a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of our late Miſeries; But they muſt pardon us, if we judg it fit to reflect upon them, ſince they ſeem ſo extreamly deſirous to involve us in them again. For upon a review of theſe Particulars, which are undeniable matters of Fact, we cannot poſſibly think that a continuance in ſuch a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Condition, was, or is, or can be a deſirable State, tho it never advanced further; much leſs can we think it tolerable, when the whole Nation were more than ſatisfied, that theſe were but the beginning of thoſe Sorrows we had ſuch a diſmal Proſpect and Apprehenſion of, had the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns afoot made a further Progreſs; And we would pray them to pardon us, that we are not willing to be ſo treacherous to our ſelves, and our Poſterity, as to throw our ſelves into that Miſery, from whence we have been ſo miraculouſly delivered.</p>
            <p>Now, tho I do not find any Man that will take upon him the impoſſible Task of juſtifying theſe Proceedings; but rather all of force muſt acknowledg there were very many Male-adminiſtrations in the Government, yet they ſtrive to excuſe them, as much as may be. I muſt tell them, would the matter bear it, we would be as willing to do it as they. And we muſt let them know, that our caſe is the more to be pitied, becauſe we were ſo like to be ruined and undone by a Prince, whom no honeſt Man in the Nation, did ever ſo much as deſire, ſhould ſall into thoſe misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes that have overtaken him; but upon the contrary, were extreamly afflicted, to ſee a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atal neceſſity of the ruin of either King or Kingdom in a very ſhort time, and would moſt willingly have contributed our utmoſt to the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it, had it lain in our Power. But this is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, the more pains men take to palliate theſe things, the more ſtill it appears, there was a wilful, fixed and unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable Reſolution of driving theſe things to the height.</p>
            <p>For while it's ſaid, That the Late King, being very zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for his Religion, and giving the Conduct of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199297:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the guidance of men ſworn to that intereſt; we cannot wonder if their perpetual ſolicitations, and unweari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed importunities, highly prevailed upon him to gratifie their deſires, in which he was withal ſatisfied that he was doing God ſingular good ſervice; this very excuſe is our greateſt Complaint. For was it not eaſie to divine what a Proteſtant Nation had reaſon to expect from a Prince alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether guided by thoſe who have ſworn their deſtruction? And the very taking of theſe men into his ſecreteſt Councils, was an open declaration to the Three Kingdoms, that their deſtruction was at no great diſtance; for we know, and all the World knows, that ſuch men as ſwarmed about <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> were employed in nothing more, than in contriving and projecting the utter deſtruction of Hereſie and Hereticks, as they account us all to be: And therefore had the late King <hi>James</hi> conſulted either his own or his Peoples ſafety, he would never have been ſo influenced by ſuch men, nor gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the leaſt ſuſpicion that he was ſo. But his making a Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit openly a great Miniſter of State, whoſe very being in the Kingdom was Treaſon; his entertaining openly a Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio from <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſwarming of Prieſts both Regular and Secular, of ſeveral Orders about him, cannot but ſhew that their Aſſumption into ſuch Privacy, ſo deſtructive to his People, was really a matter of his own mere choice.</p>
            <p>And here let me add, That the Prieſts and Jeſuits in their management of Affairs in the late King's time, were both the falſeſt and the fooliſheſt men in the world, tho they had the faireſt game to play, that ever men in their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances could wiſh for before, and fairer than I truſt they will ever obtain again. They were very falſe and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to their great Patron and Benefactor; for they conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their own intereſt ſo much, that they minded neither the Honour nor Safety of their King. For while he was driving ſo <hi>Jehu</hi> like, it was their duty faithfully to have repreſented to him, what was like to be the iſſue of ſuch proceedings, what diſhonour the ſo frequent breach of his Word muſt be, and how fatally dangerous the exaſperating of three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms muſt be; and therefore ſeriouſly to have adviſed him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:199297:9"/> to ſlower and milder methods; and to have declared their ſatisfaction, that they had rather commit the great deſign its ſelf to the Divine Providence, in methods more agreeable to the Genius of the Nation, than hazard his Majeſties Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Safety in ſuch violent and harſh meaſures. But the truth of it is, they ſaw they had nothing to rely upon, but the King's Life; and that was as uncertain as any other mans; and therefore they were willing to drive at all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly: For (ſay they) if we ſucceed, we have our aim, the day is our own; if not, we know the worſt of it, we are but where we were; we can as eaſily retire to the Cells we crept from, as we left them; but whether the King ſink or ſwim, is the leaſt of our concerns. And ah! that theſe Wretches had fallen alone, without drawing ſuch a Prince into ſuch misfortunes with them, by their precipitate Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels! Let this therefore be for ever another inſtance of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Treachery and Falſhood to their Princes; for theſe men always act as if they gloried in being the Inſtruments of the Deſtruction of Kings, or Kingdoms, or Both.</p>
            <p>And as they were the <hi>falſeſt</hi> Men to their Prince, ſo they were the <hi>fooliſheſt;</hi> for never Men took ſo improper means to attain their Ends, as they did. In truth they left nothing undone, which any man could wiſh them to do, who never ſo earneſtly wiſhed a diſappointment of all their Deſigns; as a Reverend Divine and great Man of our Church ſaid, in his Sermon on the Thankſgiving-day, they were <hi>Politicians by Book,</hi> and never conſulted the Genius and Humour of that People they had to do with. It may be they are thought very wiſe Men and great Politicians in other Countreys, but they can never in <hi>England</hi> expect any thing but the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the moſt imprudent and unpolitick of Men; and I hope this great Inſtance will be ſufficient to convince all Princes, how unſafe it is for them to truſt Men of little Honeſty, and leſs Diſcretion.</p>
            <p>If it be again ſaid, That the late King, in all theſe things ſo deſervedly decried, was inform'd of the Legality of them by his Judges, whoſe Advice in the like Caſes all our Kings have relied upon; ſo if he erred, it was their fault; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199297:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuch as do unlawful things by the King's Command, are liable to anſwer for it notwithſtanding, but not the King Himſelf. To this the Anſwer is very eaſie: The whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on knoweth very well, that when the Judges at any time gave juſt and good Advice, according to the Law, and the beſt of their knowledge, if it thwarted the Deſign intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there was a <hi>Quietus</hi> ready at hand for their deſcent from the Bench; and thus, the whole Reign of King <hi>James,</hi> there was a perpetual Change of the Judges, till they were ſo modelled, as to ſecure the Intereſt driven at; nay in the very laſt famous Tryal of the Seven Biſhops, all know, that two of the Judges were immediately removed, for giving their Opinion contrary to that Intereſt. So that it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely plain, the King was not adviſed by his Judges, but the Judges by him, how they ſhould act at their Perils, and he would have no other than ſuch as would ſerve his deſign; as for ſuch as acted by his Authority, either in Civil or Military Affairs, it's plain few or none were allowed of, but ſuch as would ſerve the Popiſh Intereſt; what meant elſe the Change of Charters; the Regulating of Corporations; the ſo frequent alterations of the Governors of them; the removing of all Officers that would not comply; the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Queſtions put ſo diligently all over the Kingdom, to Deputy-Lieutenants, Officers of the Militia, Juſtices of Peace, Magiſtrates of Cities and Boroughs, concerning Elections of future Members of Parliament? The King then was ſo far from ſuffering Perſons to be brought to Tryal for their unjuſt and illegal Actions, that as he would have no other Perſons in his Service, ſo he avowed their Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. In vain it was to expect a redreſs of theſe things, ſince even in the beginning of that Reign, when that King was ſo much obliged to the Fidelity of the Nation, for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> ſo vigorouſly, yet that very Houſe of Commons, who but a little while before, was ſo highly cajolled and careſſed by the King, went away with a Repulſe to their honeſt Addreſs, againſt Papiſts bearing Offices without legal Qualifications, and in a ſew days after, he prorogued them, and never met them more. Since then, the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199297:10"/> late King would have no other Perſons to ſerve him, nor any in places of Truſt, but ſuch as highly diſſerved the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſince he protected ſuch Perſons in all their illegal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; certainly all they did, is clearly imputable to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for ſo he would have it, and no otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>In fine, while it's ſaid, King <hi>James</hi> was lawful King of <hi>England,</hi> accountable to none for his Actions, but God only; that all we had to do, was to ſubmit either Active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or Paſſively; that our Oaths had obliged us againſt all Reſiſtance of his Majeſty, or thoſe commiſſioned by him; and therefore let the worſt be ſuppoſed that can be, we cannot juſtify our reliction of him, or transferring our Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance from him.</p>
            <p>Now in the firſt place, this is a plain acknowledgment, That we had very great cauſe of complaining; and only helps us with this Accumulation of our Miſery, we have no poſſibility of Redreſs. Now it's a deſperate Condition a Prince is brought to, that the only Juſtification of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, conſiſts in aſſerting an unlimited and uncontrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Power; and indeed, it is much the worſe, when this is done to a Nation that never have, nor never will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg themſelves to be Slaves to be ruled by the Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and Deſpotick Power of their King; but are Subjects governed by their King in the Execution of the Laws of the Land.</p>
            <p>Again, There is nothing more certain than this, That there is ſo great reference to be had to Governors and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that every ſmall irregularity in Government ought not to leſſen the Affection or Fidelity of Subjects, ſuch as Injuries accruing only to ſome private Perſons; or if they be of a publick and general Nature, yea, even againſt Laws in force; yet, if it be in matters of ſmall concern and importance, it is rather to be born with, than the Peace of the Government to be diſturbed; it is in ſuch Caſes duly to be conſidered, that nothing perfect is to be found under the Sun; that Changes and Alterations upon ſuch ſmall accounts, would render Government very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteady and uneaſy, to the main end of it, which is the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199297:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> peace of Mankind. But, what if the Caſe be ſuch, that there is no leſs attempted than the ruin of Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and Fortunes, of far the greateſt part of the Subjects? What if thoſe Laws are laid aſide, and rendred uſeleſs, which were enacted of ſet purpoſe, to ſecure the Religion and Property of all the Subjects, without ever conſulting the Legiſlative Power; nay, after a great part of that Power hath remonſtrated againſt it? What if ſuch Courſes be taken, as perfectly deſtroys the very being of Parliaments, and makes a ſummoning of them utterly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable, according to the Fundamental Conſtitutions of the Kingdom? Does not theſe, and ſuch like Proceedings, perfectly diſſolve the Government to our hands, and deprive the King of the beſt Security he hath for his Crown, to wit, the Security of the Laws ſo diſſolved? And that this was our Caſe, is apparent by what is before written: And this brings to my mind, a ſaying of the late King <hi>James,</hi> at his firſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to the Crown, <hi>That he deſired to be no greater King, than the Laws of</hi> England <hi>made him;</hi> and upon my Conſcience had he continued always in that mind, and acted accordingly, he might, nay, he would have Reigned a Glorious King, to the great Joy and Satisfaction of all his Subjects.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe it will be granted, That the end of all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the Protection and Peace, and Security of the People, by governing of them agreeably to the Laws enacted for that end; now, if this end ceaſe, and all things be acted contrary, is there not an end of that Government, with relation to the Peoples concerns in it? And in ſuch caſe, what can reaſonably be expected from them by the Laws of God, of Nature, and Self-preſervation, the firſt and great Principle of Nature, but that they ſhould look for better terms where they may have them?</p>
            <p>All this whole matter is grounded upon a falſe Opinion of Government being <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> even with relation to the ſpecies or kind of Government; nay, to the very Perſon or Family regnant; than which there cannot well be a greater Paradox; for tho it be moſt true, that Government in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, is of Divine and Natural Right; yet all the World will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199297:11"/> never be able to make either of theſe two things appear, <hi>viz.</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that this or that Species of Government, is of ſuch a right; for example, Monarchy in contradiſtinction to all other; or much leſs, that this or that family or perſon hath ſuch a Divine or natural right to ſuch or ſuch a Kingdom or Dominion: for upon this Principle we condemn all other kinds of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ſinful; we oblige our ſelves to perpetuate the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the ſame Family, in a direct Line, in the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion; a thing by the experience of all Ages known to be impoſſible, and of which this Kingdom, on ſeveral occaſions, hath taken very little notice. For he is a mighty ſtranger to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtories, who knows not that ſome Perſons have been removed from the Adminiſtration of the Regal Power, by the Authority of Parliament; and others Crowned in their ſtead, while the former were in being: and likewiſe in the Succeſſion of the Crown, little regard hath been had to the next in Proximity of Blood, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever outcry we make now; and certainly when it was Enacted in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time, That it ſhould be a <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire</hi> for any perſon to affirm, That it was not in the power of the Parliament to ſettle the Succeſſion of the Crown, they were far from dreaming of this <hi>Chimaera</hi> of Divine Right. And certainly when a Parliament in <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th's time gave that King Power to ſettle the manner of the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, and nominate the Succeſſors as he thought fit, they were far from this Divine Right too. Nay, this Opinion that men would ſo fain impoſe upon us, is deſtructive of all Right of Conqueſt or Preſcription; for againſt Divine and Natural Right, none of theſe are prevalent; for ſtill the former Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation remains to the kind of Government and Family plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch a Divine Right; which would be ſo far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the Peace of Mankind, the great End of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that it would certainly perpetuate Blood, War, and laſting Confuſions.</p>
            <p>In a word, I am ſure our Government is ſuch, as will acknowledge, That the Kings of <hi>England</hi> are bound to govern their People, not as they pleaſe, but according to the Laws of the Land: Now I would fain ask theſe few
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199297:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Queſtions upon this Conceſſion, Whether it be juſt, that the King ſhould be abſolutely ſecured by the peoples Oath of Fidelity to him; and if they break it, Gibbets, Axes, Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-Poſts, Pillories, Exile, Confiſcations of Goods, are their juſt and deſerved Puniſhments; and yet the People ſhould have no Security in the Earth, by any Oaths the King makes to them, but he is ſtill at his liberty to break them, and the People without all poſſibility of redreſs, if he do ſo? And conſequently, Whether the Coronation-Oath be a meer matter of form, and adminiſtred only to mock God and the Nation; ſince after all, the King may at pleaſure break it, and the whole Kingdom hath no remedy but <hi>God help?</hi> Whether when Chriſt and his Apoſtles preſcribed to us general Rules of Subjection and Obedience to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; they did not leave the ſeveral Nations in the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe Civil Rights they enjoy'd notwithſtanding, but engag'd Mankind to be all Slaves to the Luſt and Will of their Governours, without poſſibility of controul? Whether any acting in this Kingdom by an illegal Commiſſion, can poſſibly be eſteemed to act by the King's Commiſſion, which we are ſworn not to reſiſt; ſince it's certain that all Illegal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions are null and void in themſelves, and that Men are bound to reſiſt ſuch in their own defence; ſince the Subject is never to ſuppoſe any private Will of the King in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning of his People, contrary to the publick Will of his Laws; and is always to be ſuppoſed, that he who takes upon him the juſt defence of the Laws, is ſo far from reſiſting the King, that he is really defending of him? If the Caſe be not thus, then we certainly are commanded to ſwear, and actually do ſwear, to expoſe our Perſons, Families, Fortunes, Laws, Liberties, nay Religion it ſelf, to as many Mens Wills as may have the Conſcience to act againſt us, or ruine us in any or all theſe particulars by Illegal Commiſſions. In fine, Whether the King's being generally ſaid <hi>to do no wrong,</hi> be not to be interpreted, either becauſe he moſt commonly employs other perſons in the execution of his Commands, either Legal or Illegal; or elſe in reſpect that the King being ſworn to govern by Law, he is not to be ſuppoſed to act
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199297:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> againſt it? If the Firſt, then they that execute illegal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, are liable to be called in queſtion and puniſhed for ſo doing; but if the King protecting them with all his Power, prevent this Juſtice, doth he not then make theſe Illegal Executions his own, whether we will or no? If the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, then we are to conlude, That no Illegal Act is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Act; and conſequently, if a King either by Himſelf, or by Others commiſſionated by him, oppreſs and ruine his People in all particulars that are of greateſt concern to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, he ſo far Unkings himſelf, and puts his People upon an abſolute neceſſity of Self-defence.</p>
            <p>As for the lawfulneſs of transferring our Allegiance to Their preſent Majeſties, the Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> in his excellent Letter to his Clergy, hath ſo fully cleared that Point, that it were preſumption in me further to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Defence of it.</p>
            <p>Let me only add, That the late King ſhewed the moſt fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reſolution in the World, by his going to <hi>France;</hi> for what was this, but rather than ſuffer any Redreſs of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable Grievances of his People, he would rather for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake and abandon them, and apply himſelf to the ſworn Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of his Kingdoms, both in their Religion and Civil Rights? King <hi>James</hi> ſent to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſome Noblemen to treat with him, but had not the patience to ſtay long after the Anſwer; but rather than liſten to the calling of a Free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, withdrew himſelf voluntarily, when no Enemy was near him. His coming back again to <hi>Whitehall</hi> was a meer force put upon him; for at <hi>Feverſham,</hi> when Perſons of Quality in thoſe parts tendred him their beſt Service, his conſtant Anſwer was, <hi>The moſt acceptable ſervice you can do me, is to facilitate my departure, and procure means for my going beyond Sea:</hi> And whatever noiſe is made about his leaving <hi>Whitehall</hi> the ſecond time, yet it's plain his reſolution was ſtill to depart, as a thing he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt ſolemnly engaged to do; and ſo to leave his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, rather than enter upon fair and legal ways of giving them ſatisfaction: and this the Lords and Commons in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, as freely choſen as ever Repreſentatives were to any Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> have avowed to be an <hi>Abdication of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199297:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> his Government,</hi> and <hi>Vacating of his Throne.</hi> And I would know but theſe two things in this particular, Whether, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we were left by the King's departure, any better, juſter, or ſpeedier courſe could be taken, to ſave the Nation from thoſe Miſeries and Confuſions it muſt neceſſarily have fallen into, in that ſtate of Anarchy the King left us, than that of calling ſuch a Convention? And then, Whether ſuch a Convention, ſo freely called and choſen, when met, doth not conclude the Nation by their Reſolutions, ſince all knew their Election was for this very purpoſe, to reſtore us the Happineſs of a ſettled State, and by electing of them, inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Themſelves and their Conſents to their Reſolves, as much as ever they did in other Elections to Parliament. As for thoſe Redreſſes that were made juſt upon the News of the Prince's Intention for <hi>England,</hi> they were done at ſuch a time as too plainly ſhewed it to be the product of Fear and Neceſſity, not of Choice; and it's well known, that what Kings in ſtraits are forced to do; when free, they voluntarily and readily undo; and the worſt wiſh I wiſh King <hi>James</hi> is, That what he did then, he had done a twelve-month before; tho even then the greateſt matters continued as they were, <hi>viz.</hi> Perſons in all Offices of Truſt without legal qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by virtue of the Diſpenſing Power, then not in the leaſt diſowned.</p>
            <p>By what I have ſaid, it plainly appears, that our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, when their Majeſties arrived here, was moſt deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, without any hope of a redreſs, our Miſeries daily growing upon us; and it's not uneaſie for any man to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, what our Caſe muſt certainly have been, had not God raiſed up this mighty Deliverer, our preſent King, to put a ſtop to thoſe unhappy Proceedings; and if we be ſo inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this great Deliverance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo ſoon have forgot our former Thraldom, and our juſt fears of worſe; I can ſay no more, but that we are as bad as the <hi>Iſraeliets,</hi> deſiring <hi>Egypt</hi> again, when their faces were towards <hi>Canaan;</hi> and luſting for the Fleſh-pots there, when they were feeding on Angels Food. And ſo I come to ſhew the danger of our Relapſe, by conſidering the happy Eſtate and Condition we are in by this bleſſed Revolution.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:199297:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>We may take up in theſe Nations that Song of <hi>David, When the Lord turned again the Captivity of Sion, then were we like unto them that dream.</hi> The Deliverance was ſo ſtrange and wonderful, that it appeared plainly the Lord's doing, and therefore mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous in our eyes. We may look upon the Providence that gave the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> our now moſt Gracious King, ſo juſt a right to ſuccour us, as wonderful, even that happy day, wherein the Auſpicious Marriage of that Royal Pair was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated, to the great joy and laſting ſecurity of the Peace and Happineſs of theſe Nations. This was, I am ſure, a great earneſt of the Divine Goodneſs, and a happy Omen of this bleſſed Fruit of it.</p>
            <p>I know not what to admire moſt at in this prodigious Deliverance; That a matter of ſo great importance, that muſt of neceſſity be communicated to ſeveral perſons both at home and abroad, ſhould take no air all the while, till juſt it was ready to be executed; ſo that the Deliverance was ſudden and unexpected, no-ways looked for at that time, or in that manner, is ſcarce to be exemplified: the means uſed to effect this Deſign, being ſo unproportionate to this great end deſigned, makes the ſucceſs a Prodigy. The extent of this Bleſſing is not the leaſt thing conſiderable in it; it is general to the whole Nation, every one ſhares in the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; thoſe only excepted, that would fain have made us miſerable. For as the Religion and Civil Intereſts of all were equally in danger, ſo the Security of both is extenſive to all: Nay, this Revolution ſecures Truth, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it, to other Nations; for it's well known what hazard the Proteſtant Religion every-where had been in, had it been ſubverted in this famous Iſland. And therefore, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ungrateful we may be, who yet have the more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate advantage of it; yet I am ſure all Proteſtant <hi>Europe</hi> are li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting up their Hearts, Hands and Tongues in the Praiſes of the God of Truth, who hath ſo ſignally appeared for our Deliverance; and in that, for their ſecurity.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:199297:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Let us look upon our preſent Condition; Would we be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be happy, and compare it to what we were a Twelve-Month ago? then we were almoſt in Deſpair, ſadly thinking with our ſelves, to what ſtrange Countries we ſhould repair to avoid the impending Storm; our Biſhops were thrown into Priſons, our Clergy threatned with Deprivations and Suſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, our Univerſities purſued with <hi>Quo Warranto's,</hi> our Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges invaded by the Locuſts of <hi>Egypt;</hi> the Abomination of the Maſs, and Idolatry and Superſtition of Popery ſet up in all the Corners of City and Countrey; our Judges carrying about Shavelings, to preach before them in their Circuits; and they themſelves in their Charges, at Aſſizes, preaching Sermons of Tranſubſtantiation, and Submiſſion to the See of <hi>Rome:</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants diſcountenanced, diſcarded, diſgraced; Papiſts every where, in City, in Countrey, in Court, in Armies, in Forts, in Navies, in Corporations, in Counties, lording it over us. Parliaments intended us worſe than none, the Complement of our Miſeries being expected from them, as Elections were then ordered; which made all good Men wiſh from their Souls, That whatever our Condition was, or might be, yet we might never ſee a Parliament ſit in <hi>England,</hi> during King <hi>James</hi> the Second's Reign; ſince they would never be ſuffered to do us good, and in all probability could not fail in doing us much harm.</p>
            <p>The Caſe is quite altered now, as is obvious at firſt ſight; our Religion hath the greateſt Security, our Biſhops and Clergy the greateſt Protection, our Vacant Biſhopricks are filled with the moſt wiſe and learned of the Clergy, Colledges are reſtored to their proper Owners; the Idolatry of Popery dare not ſhew it ſelf any where; the Wind hath blown theſe Locuſts of Prieſts, Jeſuits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beyond the Seas, to their former Lurking-Places; every one ſits ſafe under his own Vine, enjoying ſecurely the Liberty of an Engliſhman, the Property he is poſſeſt of; our Councils, Navies, Armies, Magiſtrates, are Proteſtants; and a Security to our Religion, dearer to us than our Lives: our Judges are as at the firſt, and our Counſellors as at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:199297:14"/>
            <p>Pray Gentlemen recount with your Selves, What was our greateſt Hope, our only Comfort on Earth, in thoſe Days of our Duſtreſs? What was it that ſuſtained our Spirits and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from utter Diſpair? What did we diſcourſe of every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where to one another, as the ſole Foundation of our Hopes of Freedom and Relief? Was it not that the King was a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Man, and after him we had a Reſerve of the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> for our Security? How often then did we caſt our Eyes and Hearts upon the <hi>Belgick</hi> Shore, truſting that at laſt the Providence of God would whaft over that bleſſed Pair to the laſting Joy of this <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſland? The Papiſts knew this very well, and could never think themſelves ſafe, till theſe Princes Intereſts were defeated, and thereby, as they thought, all our Hopes fruſtrate. But God that brings Good out of the greateſt Evil, by his infinite Wiſdom and Power, converted that Project by which they intended to perpetuate the Slavery of theſe Nations, to an accelerating or haſtening our Deliverance, ſooner than ever we hoped for it; for never was there a juſter Cauſe given any Prince, to quarrel with a Poſſeſſor, than was given the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> when he ſaw not only all our Laws violated, and the People of <hi>England</hi> enſlaved, but likewiſe his juſt Intereſt in the Crown, in Right of his Princeſs the immediate Heir, ſo violently invaded, without any Satisfaction given, uſual in ſuch Caſes, of the Sincerity of that Affair of the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> in which not only this whole Nation was violently ſuſpicious, upon very great Grounds, but likewiſe the intended Fraud was the Diſcourſe of <hi>Europe.</hi> This Matter hath been ſufficiently written of, and for my part, if there were no more to create a Diffidence in me not poſſible of receiving any Satisfaction, this would be more than ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that I never heard of any Satisfaction given, to the Great and Vertuous Lady the Princeſs <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Denmark</hi> in this whole Affair; and yet it was highly juſt ſhe ſhould have received it, in reſpect of her Proximity to the Crown; and likewiſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of that Fruitful Womb, God hath been pleaſed to bleſs her Highneſs with, whoſe Children have a very fair Proſpect to the Royal Inheritance: it had been likewiſe very eaſy to have done it, becauſe her Highneſs was perpetually upon the very
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199297:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> place where the Scene was acting, juſt till the time of its finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then it was moſt neceſſary ſhe ſhould have been there; and it's impoſſible to imagine, had it been a real Thing, care would have been taken that ſhe ſhould have been preſent; but on the other Hand, if it was not real, then it was altogether neceſſary, that of all Perſons ſhe ſhould be out of the way, and ſuch care was accordingly taken: And as her Satisfaction was both juſt and eaſy, ſo it would have been of mighty advantage to the convincing of the Nation of the Truth of it, her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe's Evidence would have been of more weight, than all thoſe at Council-Board, in reſpect none will bear witneſs againſt their own Intereſt, eſpecially in a matter of ſo great Moment, unleſs it be very true. All the anſwer ever I could hear to this moſt material ground of Suſpicion, is, either that there was no Obligation to give any ſuch Satisfaction, or that the Princeſs did not deſire it, and was not curious of being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. To which this is only fit to be ſaid by way of Reply, that the firſt is a deſperate, and the ſecond a ſenſeleſs Anſwer. Is it not then a great Favour of God to us, that the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance we ſo earneſtly wiſhed, and the Perſons on whom our Eyes were fixed, are thus come to our Deliverance? our very Enemies haſtening it ſooner than ever we looked for it.</p>
            <p>Is it not the Joy of all good Men, who love the Proſperity of our <hi>Sion,</hi> and pray for her Peace, to ſee a Proteſtant King and Queen in <hi>England,</hi> a Happineſs <hi>Britain</hi> hath not been fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured with, ſince the Death of Queen <hi>Ann</hi> the Wife of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt? We have no <hi>Dalilah</hi> in the Boſom of our <hi>Sampſon,</hi> to allure him to betray his own and the Nations Strength, that we may be the eaſier Prey to the <hi>Philiſtines:</hi> The Marriage of our Kings, to Ladies of the Popiſh Perſuaſion, hath been ſo plain a Cauſe of the Nations Miſery, that we have great cauſe to rejoice in ſo happy a ſight, as both King and Queen to be of the ſame Religion, and that which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and eſtabliſhed Religion of their Kingdoms: and its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be hoped, the Wiſdom of our Parliament will make it no ſmall part of their Care, to prevent the Miſchiefs that have ſo conſtantly attended our Kings being ſo unequally yoked. Our King and Queen draw not now ſeveral Ways, their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199297:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> are the ſame; as they are in Bed and at Board one, ſo it's our great Comfort to ſee them repair to the ſame Churches, exerciſed in the ſame Devotions, addreſſing to the ſame Altar; in a word, of the ſame Faith and Religion, to the great encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of their Subjects, to follow ſo pious, ſo great an Example: So that there are no hopes now of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> plowing with <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Heifer. The Royal Intereſt is now abſolutely the ſame with that of the People; for their Majeſties and their People, are more ſurely tyed together by the Bonds of that Religion, for which both have an equal Zeal, than by any Political Obligations whatſoever; ſo that now both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in the mutual Proſperity of each other, their Majeſties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicing in their Peoples Security, and they again in the Royal Protection, as in all Things, ſo chiefly in that which is the beſt of all Things, Religion.</p>
            <p>Neither are we to neglect the Conſideration of that, which deſervedly makes his preſent Majeſty the Darling of theſe three Kingdoms, nay, like another <hi>Titus,</hi> the Delight of Mankind, <hi>viz.</hi> that the King, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> had no ſuch great matters to look for as to his own Intereſt, to move him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter ſo great Dangers, to undergo ſo much Trouble. He was conſiderably great in the <hi>Low-Countries;</hi> he hath no Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to enjoy the Crown after his own Death: ſo that it plainly appears his Zeal for Religion, his great concern for the bleeding ſtate of theſe Nations, his love to Juſtice, did much more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with him to this Heroick and Glorious Undertaking, than any concern of his own in the Caſe.</p>
            <p>Now upon the whole, if we deſpiſe ſo wonderful a Mercy, and become ſo bereft of Reaſon as to be weary of Happineſs, and court perpetual Slavery, and abandon our preſent Security and Tranquillity, for thoſe Miſeries we have reaſon to look for upon ſuch an unwiſe change; What can we then expect but to be treated by God as the deſpiſers of his greateſt Goodneſs, and to periſh without ſo much as the pity of Men, ſince we knew not how to prize a laſting Security, when we had it in our Hands, and conſequently that our Relapſe muſt be very miſerable to us?</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:199297:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But if at laſt we propoſe to our Selves the Miſeries that muſt unavoidably fall upon us; if the Sins of this Nation ſo provoke God, as to bereave us of that Happineſs we now enjoy, and if we be wiſe may entail it upon our Poſterity, by another Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution ſome Men ſo eagerly deſire, we cannot but be convinced that a Relapſe is highly dangerous; I do profeſs, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities that fatally attend ſuch a Revolution, are ſo tremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous and horrible, that the very apprehenſion of them cannot but ſtrike conſiderate Men into the greateſt Confuſion and Amazement: we can expect nothing elſe, but that our Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhould occaſion our being a Proverb and a By-word, a hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and reproach of Popiſh Nations, who gape for our Ruine, and greedily thirſt after our Deſtruction; and on the other Hand, that we ſhould be followed with Execrations and Curſes, from the Proteſtant World, for ſo treacherouſly betraying that Truth we had ſo great a Zeal for; that a Nation that glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo juſtly in being accounted the Bulwark of the Proteſtant Religion, ſhould ſo fatally occaſion the total overthrow of it.</p>
            <p>I will but briefly recount ſome of thoſe Miſchiefs, that any reaſonable Man cannot but apprehend muſt overtake us upon ſuch a Relapſe; if we conſider with what Rage and Fury, with what thirſt of Revenge, not only the late King, (whoſe natural Temper doth not much diſpoſe him to a forgetting of Injuries) but all of the Popiſh Party muſt return amongſt us, what are we to expect? Is the late King ever the leſs a Papiſt than before? Hath he abated any thing of his Zeal for that Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition? Have the Jeſuits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> any other Sentiments of us and our Religion than they had? ask the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and they will inform you, who fly as faſt out of that Kingdom, as ever the French Refuges forſook <hi>France.</hi> If we were ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly uſed when we had given no Offence, what are we to look for when the worſt of Crimes ſhall be laid to our Charge? If our Religion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear loſt, our Laws and Liberties invaded, when all the Obligations of the Earth were upon the Prince to protect them, how utterly muſt all be loſt, when the Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſo late Affronts, ſhall expoſe us to all the direful Effects of an ungoverned Zeal, and enraged Revenge?</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:199297:16"/>
            <p>But beſides, How are we to expect that ſuch a Revolution ſhould be brought about? I am very confident <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> will never be willing to afford ſo great a Strength as is ſufficient for ſuch an Enterprize; ſome hot-headed Men may aſſiſt a ſtronger Party from Abroad, but they will never undertake to do it alone: No, no, we plainly ſee it's an <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French Power</hi> muſt do this; thence Men, Money, and Arms muſt come: this is ſo certain, that I do not believe any Man in the Nation ſo bereft of Senſe, as to expect it any other way. And now what a Train of Miſeries this Dragons-Tail draws after it, is not eaſy either to be thought or expreſt: if ever ſuch a diſmal Calamity ſhould befal us, we ſhall want ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to write the <hi>Lamentations</hi> of our <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> I do not think that ever any Nation under Heaven was expoſed to a more barbarous Deſolation, than this poor Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be upon ſuch an unhappy Change. How hath the French King uſed his own Subjects, to whom by the Oaths of God, upon his Soul, he owed all Protection? and if ſo cruel at Home, what are we Strangers to expect from his Armies, but all the Outrages that attend an inſulting Conqueſt, of an Enemy, who hath reſolved our Ruine, and ſworn the Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Religion? If the cutting us off from being a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould be the price of it; what are we to expect, whoſe unhappy Connivance hath occaſioned all his Greatneſs, and whoſe Strength and Riches, are the Shears that now clips his Wings, from ſoaring to that height of Univerſal Empire, he ſo vainly and proudly graſps at? And the Truth is, this is a great Miſery, that upon ſuch a Change the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is moſt likely to devolve, not from King <hi>William</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> but from King <hi>William</hi> to King <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> which the great God of Heaven avert. We have heard of Princes ſpoſled of their Dominions by that King, but never could hear yet of any Prince reſtored by him. Can it poſſibly enter into the Thoughts of any reaſonable Man, that the King of <hi>France</hi> will employ his Forces by Sea and Land, and ſpend his Treaſures, in conquering of theſe Kingdoms, and then quietly deliver them up to another to poſſeſs? who himſelf labours ſo deeply of the Dropſy of enlarging his Dominions, that neither Faith of Treaties, Laws of Nations, Oath of God,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199297:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> nor the ſence of common Equity and Juſtice, could ever yet bind him, from making the moſt unjuſt Encroachments upon his Neighbours wherever he could. And this is the more to be conſidered, becauſe it's very eaſy to believe that the Popiſh Clergy of <hi>England</hi> would be willing enough it ſhould be ſo, King <hi>Lewis</hi> being more able to maintain his Conqueſt, than King <hi>James</hi> can ever be ſuppoſed to be to maintain his Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and their Security; and if the Popiſh Clergy may juſtly be ſuppoſed to become ſo indifferent in this caſe, it's eaſy to foreſee, how the Laity of that Perſuaſion might be induced to a Satisfaction, ſince theſe ſo ſlaviſhly, and indeed ſo brutiſhly, hang their Conſciences at thoſe Mens Girdles; ſo that upon the whole, King <hi>Lewis</hi> is like to be the only Gainer, altho I am far from thinking that they who make this noiſe amongſt us, aim at any ſuch thing, yet it is worth their while ſeriouſly to conſider, whether it will lye in their Power to prevent or help it.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> their Carriage to Proteſtants in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt's Time, and now to the Proteſtants at this very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, is more than ſufficient to ſatisfy us what Meaſures we are to expect from them; their natural Barbarity, their conſtant Averſion to the Engliſh Nation, their thirſt after a Repriſal upon Proteſtants Eſtates, to make up the pretended Damages they have ſuſtained, their ignorant and blind Zeal for a rooted Superſtition, are too much to convince us, with what Intentions they muſt invade us; and what are like to be the Effects of their barbarous Cruelty? In a word, it's Papiſts are certainly to be employed to do this grand Feat, who will be ſure to give the Proteſtants, that ſhall be ſo unwiſe as to aſſiſt them, the ſame Thanks that Queen <hi>Mary</hi> gave thoſe of <hi>Suffolk;</hi> that the King of <hi>France</hi> hath given his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants; and that the late King <hi>James</hi> did ſo lately give the Church of <hi>England;</hi> they will find, at laſt, to their Coſt, the Effects of that unalterable Maxim amongſt them, <hi>That no Faith is to be kept with Hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then how is it poſſible for us, without the higheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in the World, to repreſent to our ſelves the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:199297:17"/> of ſuch a Change, with relation to their preſent Majeſties, and the Princeſs <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Denmark?</hi> I am very loth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt too long upon this, its ſo extreamly Tragical; Is this the Gratitude we owe to the moſt magnanimous, couragious, and charitable Undertaking, that ever was, to reſcue three Nations out of the Jaws of Popery and Slavery? Can we find in our Heart to expoſe our great Deliverer to ſo much Danger in his Perſon, and Ruine in his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, who ſo readily ventured Life and Fortune for our Good? Can we ſo willingly deprive our ſelves of all our Hopes repoſed in theſe Proteſtant Branches of the Royal Family, as for ever to render them uncapable of doing us any further Kindneſs, or affording us any further Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? Have we ſo little ſenſe of the moſt ſteadfaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and the unmovable Fidelity of theſe great Perſons, to the Religion and Intereſt of theſe Nations, which could never be byaffed by the Authority of a King and Father, nor ſhaken by the violent Temptations, and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults upon their Conſtancy? Who by their fixed Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions to adhere to our Intereſts, had the worſt of Arts uſed to deſeat them of their juſt Rights; for would they have but complyed with the Deſigns projected againſt us, I dare ſay neither they nor we had ever been troubled with a Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi> Can we expect in another De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of Miſery, to have another Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully and miraculouſly to draw us out of it: No, no, it's to be hoped the Nation will never be prevailed upon to incur the Guilt of ſuch Ingratitude to Perſons we owe our Religion, Laws and Liberties to: We will never do that which will ſo juſtly expoſe us to the Cenſures of the World, and render us unworthy, in any Circumſtances, of any Foreign Aſſiſtance, ſo utterly inconſiſtent with the Safety of thoſe who afford it. In a Word, we will be ſo juſt to our Selves, as not to entail Popery and Bondage to our Poſterity; for if we loſe theſe great Perſons, where can we fix our hopes of any Relief?</p>
            <p>Can we likewiſe, without Aſtoniſhment, think upon the Condition of Lords and Commons, in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199297:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> in caſe of any ſuch Change of Affairs, without Horror? Have we choſen ſo many worthy Patriots, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent us there, only to expoſe them to the greateſt Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs? Have they been ſo faithful to re-ſettle us into a moſt happy Condition, by ſecuring our Religion, Laws, and Liberties, to be left at laſt to the Fury and Malice of Popiſh Vengeance? Did the Famous Nobility and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Gentry of this Kingdom, venture all for the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Nation, to no other purpoſe, than to loſe Honour, Eſtate, Life, and all, for their Zeal to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Love to their Country? Surely as we cannot but believe, that this muſt be the Conſequence of ſuch an unhappy Change, with relation to the Nobility and Gentry of this Kingdom; ſo it's not to be doubted but that all <hi>England</hi> will conceive a juſt Indignation, againſt ſuch Ingratitude, and will apprehend themſelves obliged to eſpouſe their Intereſt cordially and unanimouſly, who have ſo wiſely, and with ſo much Courage, ſecured to us all Things capable of our utmoſt Eſteem.</p>
            <p>In a word, when we ſeriouſly conſider the great Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the Proteſtant Intereſt is expoſed to all over <hi>Europe,</hi> that nothing leſs is intended, than the rooting out of that vile peſtilent <hi>Northern Hereſy,</hi> as the Enemies of our Holy Religion are pleaſed to call it; I hope we will think more than once upon it, before we contribute ſo highly, to the utter Subverſion of the Proteſtant Religion in general every where, as the cutting off of theſe three Kingdoms from it muſt neceſſarily occaſion. It's well known that theſe Churches of Great <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and more particularly that of <hi>England,</hi> have been juſtly look'd upon, as the Bulwark of the Proteſtant Religion in general; and therefore the Papiſts have uſed their utmoſt Fraud in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining of her, and their utmoſt Violence in raiſing up their Batteries againſt her, aſſuring themſelves, if they could but once gain this Bulwark, they would quickly, and with Eaſe make themſelves Maſters of the whole Fort; it's well known, that the French King durſt never have uſed his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Subjects, as he both perfidiouſly and barbarouſly did,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199297:18"/> if <hi>England</hi> had had the liberty to have eſpouſed their Intereſt, and it was juſtly look'd upon as a wonderful Thing, that the King of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be declaring himſelf ſo much for Liberty of Conſcience here, and yet on the other ſide of the Water, the French King ſhould be uſing all ſorts of Cruelties upon thoſe of our Religion wholly to extirpate it, and yet King <hi>James</hi> ſhould never become their Interceſſor, nor declare to that King his juſt Reſentments of his Acting ſo contrary to his conſtant Principles, eſpecially when his uſing his Subjects ſo could not but ſtrike all his own Engliſh Subjects into an Alarm, and put them upon ſadly divining what in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility was like to be their own Fate in time. Why have the Proteſtant Princes and States entered into ſo ſtrong a Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, looking upon their preſent Majeſties as the Chief ſupport of it, but upon the certain knowledg they had, of a Deſign on Foot to ruin them? and thus it may be eaſily conjectur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what muſt be the Danger of the Proteſtant Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, if <hi>England</hi> be rendred uncapable of giving Aſſiſtance to its Profeſſors; nay more, if the ſtrength of <hi>England</hi> be made uſe of to promote their Deſtruction. But its obvious this muſt be the reſult of the return of Popery and Slavery amongſt us; ſo that upon the whole Matter, if ever ſuch a Judgment from Heaven, ſhould overtake us, as the return of this unclean Spirit of <hi>Popery,</hi> and its Uſher <hi>Slavery,</hi> among us, we cannot but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that not only Seven, but a Legion of Miſeries worſe then we have felt, muſt return with it, ſufficient to make our laſt Caſe worſe then our firſt.</p>
            <p>The Caſe being ſo plainly thus, is it poſſible that Men can ever be in love with ſuch Miſeries as theſe, not only upon themſelves, but upon their Innocent Poſterity. For the Word is <hi>Now or Never,</hi> and <hi>Now and Ever.</hi> And that we may never feel the Miſchiefs of the laſt part of this Sentence, I hope we will take Care to Secure the firſt, that becauſe not <hi>now</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they <hi>never</hi> ſhall prevail upon us. I beſeech you, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who ſeem to be ſo willing to bereave us of our preſent Tranquillity, and to contribute what in you lies to bring a Deluge of Miſeries upon us, in which you your ſelves muſt certainly be overwhelmed, if ever you be truly Zealous for,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:199297:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> and faithful to the Truth of God profeſt in this Nation; I pray you to conſider with your Selves, that if your Deſires ſhould ſucceed, and you ſhould be aiding and aſſiſting to it, what late Repentance and Horror muſt ſeize upon you, while you ſhall ſadly then, when it is to late, reflect upon that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction you have brought upon your Country and Fellow-Country-Men, and it's not to be doubted, but at laſt upon your Selves too!</p>
            <p>But if Men will continue obſtinate in Miſchief, and are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to uſe their utmoſt Endeavours to ruſh us again into Confuſions, and to ſet all in a Flame, it's to be hoped his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will have ſuch a ſpecial regard to the Welfare of theſe Nations, in which that of his own, and all the Proteſtant Branches of the Royal Family, is ſo cloſely wrapt up, that he will moſt diligently inſpect into the wicked Practices, and moſt villanous Deſigns of ſuch ill-minded-Men; and indeed they ought betimes to bethink themſelves, what the whole Kingdom muſt think thoſe Men worthy of, who are Haters of their Peace, and Contrivers of their Deſtruction: for what ever Eyes they look with, and whatſoever Proſpective-Glaſs they make uſe of, they muſt pardon us, who can ſee nothing but laſting Miſery, attending their Projects and Deſigns: and therefore however they may hope his Majeſtys Clemency (which by their undutiful Language, bold and ungrateful Speeches, and inſolent Attempts, in the Face of a Nation, reſolved to continue their Happineſs, by moſt conſtantly adhering to his Majeſties Intereſts) they have already too much tryed; yet they are Fools to imagine his Majeſty will ſuffer his innate Lenity and Gentleneſs, to be the greateſt Cruelty to his faithful Subjects, by extending it to Perſons obſtinately bent upon his and their Ruin; nor can they dream, that a whole Nation, now ſecured of all that's dear to them, will much longer bear the bantering Affronts, and not only undutiful, but even Treaſonable Practices of ſuch Men who ſo carry themſelves, as if they longed for nothing more than our Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And juſt as I was writing this, came to my Hands that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, pretended to be a Declaration from King <hi>James</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199297:19"/> to all his Loving Subjects in the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> Perhaps there was never a greater piece of Inſolence acted in any Nation, than diſperſing of theſe in a Kingdom, where there is a King <hi>de facto</hi> upon the Throne; and the Reſentment the Houſe of Commons has ſhewed, is a ſufficient proof of what I have juſt now ſaid; but for the Paper it ſelf, it carries all the Marks of Forgery that poſſibly can be: for would ever the late King tell his Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> of his kind uſage to his Proteſtant Subjects in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who are ſo infallibly convinc'd of the contrary? For why ſhould ſo many of the Biſhops and Clergy, ſo many People of all Conditions fly out of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, even ſince his arrival there, and leave their Eſtates and Habitations, and caſt themſelves upon the Charity of <hi>England</hi> for a preſent Subſiſtance, if this Libel were true? Why, even at this very Time, do they embrace all opportunities of Tranſporting themſelves, into this Iſland, with great Joy and Thankfulneſs? If Proteſtant Perſons, Fortunes, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, were in ſo much Safety, what makes the Proteſtants of <hi>Londonderry, &amp;c.</hi> rather venture their Lives in their own Defence, and endure the Perils and hardſhip of a dangerous Siege, if the Proteſtants there were in ſo great Security? Surely the Forgers of this Libel imagine it poſſible to put out our very Eyes, and to hood-wink us to Deſtruction. Can we ever think that Proteſtants will ever be ſafe, or apprehend themſelves ſo, where the French domineer, at the rate they muſt certainly be preſumed to do in <hi>Ireland?</hi> For it's very reaſonable to conclude that ſeeing Men, Ammunition, Money, and whatſoever is neceſſary for War, cometh from the French, that King will, nay, muſt rule the Roaſt. We will therefore believe our own Intelligence much better then this piece of Forgery, <hi>viz.</hi> that the very Papiſts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> are ſo appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of the French Tyranny, that they begin to wiſh for the mild Government of Proteſtant <hi>England,</hi> rather than ly under the inſupportable Tyranny of Popiſh <hi>France.</hi> As for the large Promiſes made to <hi>England</hi> upon a ſurrender theſe Forgerers invite us to, I have ſaid enough already, that Popiſh Faith can never be more truned by Proteſtants, and we are very well aſſured, that if it were poſſible for the Hoſt of Heaven to come down upon Earth, to be Guarantee for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199297:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Fidelity of Papiſts to Proteſtants in any Treaties made with them relating to Religion; they would notwithſtanding, upon the firſt ſafe Opportunity, violate them; and if theſe bleſſed Spirits ſhould take upon them the Deſence of the Guarantee and the Honour of it, they would preſently diſown their Patronage, and deprive them of the Honour of their being their Interceſſors, and charge them with being Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers of the vileſt Hereticks; for we would deſire but one Inſtance wherein ever Proteſtants were uſed kindly by Papiſts where ever it was in their Power to uſe them otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Go on then, Great Sir, in the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that, which your Majeſty hath ſo gloriouſly begun, and ſo magnanimouſly undertaken, and have had the aſſiſtance of the God of Truth, to the Joy of theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to the Deſpair and Confuſion of your Enemies, to the Security of the Proteſtant World; your Majeſtie hath the Hearts, the Hands, the Purſes of your People at your Devotion; you have a Parliament, who having engaged whatſoever is worthy of Men of Honour, of Fortune, of Religion for your Aſſiſtance, will never be wanting to enable you to compleat Yours, Theirs, Ours, nay <hi>Europe</hi>'s Happineſs; You have the greateſt Security of the Protection of that God, who is the Diſpoſer of Kingdoms, by whom Kings reign, who hath hitherto bleſſed you with Succeſs to a Miracle, You have, in fine, the beſt and moſt Glorious
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199297:20"/> Cauſe, even the preſerving of theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (to which God, and Nature, and a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral conſent of your People, have given you ſuch a cloſe Intereſt and near Relation) from all the Calamities that could befall either the Souls, Bodies, or Fortunes of Us and our Poſterity. This I am ſure is the hearty Prayer of all that are lovers either of our Civil or Religious Rights, and our ſecure, peaceable, and laſting enjoyment of them, <hi>that your Enemies may be clothed with ſhame, but upon your Head the Crown may long Flouriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:199297:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwel.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Caſe of Allegiance in our preſent Circumſtances conſidered, in a Letter from a Miniſter in the City to a Miniſter in the Country.</item>
               <item>A Sermon preached at <hi>Fulham,</hi> in the Chappel of the Palace, upon <hi>Eaſter</hi>-Day 1689, at the Conſecration of the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>Gilbert</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum:</hi> By <hi>Anthony Horneck,</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>The Judgments of God upon the <hi>Roman Catholick Church,</hi> from its firſt rigid Laws for univerſal Conformity to it, unto its laſt End. VVith a proſpect of theſe near approaching Revolutions, <hi>viz.</hi> The Revival of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Profeſſion in an eminent Kingdom, where it was totally ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The laſt End of all <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Hoſtilities. The general Mortification of the Power of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> in all parts of its Dominions. In Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Trumpets</hi> and <hi>Vials</hi> of the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> upon Principles generally acknowledged by <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Interpreters. By <hi>Drue Creſſener,</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>A Breviate of the State of <hi>Scotland</hi> in its Government, Supream Courts, Officers of State, Inferiour Officers, Offices and Inferiour Courts, Diſtricts, Juriſdictions, Burroughs Royal, and Free Corporations. <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some Conſiderations touching Succeſſion and Allegiance. 4<hi>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe concerning the Worſhip of Images; preached before the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford.</hi> By <hi>George Tully,</hi> Sub-Dean of <hi>York,</hi> for which he was ſuſpended.</item>
               <item>Reflections upon the late Great Revolution: Written by a Lay-Hand in the Country, for the ſatisfaction of ſome Neighbours.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of the Diſſertion; or an Account of all the publick Affairs in <hi>England,</hi> from the beginning of <hi>September,</hi> 1688. to the Twelfth of <hi>February</hi> following. With an Anſwer to a Piece call'd the Diſſertion diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed, in a Letter to a Country-Gentleman. By a Perſon of Quality.</item>
               <item>K. <hi>William</hi> and K. <hi>Lewis,</hi> wherein is ſet forth the inevitable neceſſity theſe Nations lie under of ſubmitting wholly to one or other of theſe Kings; And that the matter in Controverſy is not now between K. <hi>William</hi> and K. <hi>James,</hi> but between K. <hi>William</hi> and K. <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of theſe Nations.</item>
               <item>An Examination of the Scruples of thoſe who refuſe to take the Oath of Allegiance, by a Divine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Dialogue betwixt two Friends, a <hi>Jacobite</hi> and a <hi>Williamite;</hi> occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the late Revolution of Affairs, and the Oath of Allegiance.</item>
               <item>Two Sermons, one againſt Murmuring, the other againſt Cenſuring: By <hi>Symon Patrick,</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>An Account of the Reaſons which induced <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>England,</hi> to declare War againſt the <hi>States General</hi> of the United Provinces in 1672. And of the <hi>Private League</hi> which he entred into at the ſame Time with the <hi>French King</hi> to carry it on, and to eſtabliſh Popery in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they are ſet down in the <hi>Hiſtory of the Duten
<pb facs="tcp:199297:21"/> War,</hi> printed in <hi>French</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> with the Priviledg of the French King, 1682. Which Book he cauſed to be immediately ſuppreſs'd at the Inſtance of the Engliſh Ambaſſador. <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Account of the Private League betwixt the late King <hi>James</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and the <hi>French</hi> King. <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Caſe of Oaths Stated. 4<hi>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Anſwer of a Proteſtant Gentleman in <hi>Ireland</hi> to a late Popiſh Letter of <hi>N. N.</hi> upon a Diſcourſe between them, concerning the preſent Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of that Countrey, and the Part fit for thoſe concern'd there to act in it. 4<hi>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Apology for the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in a brief Narrative of the late Revolutions in that Kingdom; and an Account of the preſent State thereof: By a Gentleman of Quality. 4<hi>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter from a French Lawyer to an Engliſh Gentleman, upon the Preſent Revolution. 4<hi>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Wake</hi>'s Sermon before the King and Queen at <hi>Hampton-Court.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Faſt-Sermon before the Houſe of Commons, <hi>June</hi> 5. 1689.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Tenniſon</hi>'s Sermon againſt Self-love, before the Houſe of Commons, <hi>June</hi> 5. 1689.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Tully</hi>'s Sermon of Moderation, before the Lord-Mayor, <hi>May</hi> 12. 1689.</item>
               <item>A Letter written by the Emperor to the late King <hi>James,</hi> ſetting forth the true Occaſion of his Fall, and the Treachery and Cruelty of the French.</item>
               <item>The Reſolution of the Electors, and the Princes of the Empire, <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> 11. 1689. Containing the Reaſons of their Declaring War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt France: Together with the Emperor's Concurrence with them in it, and approving the ſame.</item>
               <item>An Account of the late Revolution in <hi>New-England.</hi> Together with the Declaration of the Gentlemen, Merchants, and Inhabitants of <hi>Boſton,</hi> and the Country adjacent, <hi>April</hi> 18. 1689. Written by Mr. <hi>Nathanael Byfield,</hi> a Merchant of <hi>Briſtol</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> to his Friends in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Declaration of his Electoral Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> concerning the preſent War with <hi>France:</hi> Directing his Subjects and Vaſſals, and all other His Dependants, how they are to demean themſelves in their Trading, Negotiation, and all incident Occaſions during the preſent War. As alſo a Letter ſent from the Imperial Diet at <hi>Ratisbon,</hi> to the Thirteen Cantons In <hi>Switzerland, March</hi> 7. 1689. Exhorting hem to adhere to his Imperial Majeſty, and the Princes of the Empire, in the preſent War againſt <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
